<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Adrienne's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://adriennefishman.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adriennefishman.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-11T21:30:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://adriennefishman.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adrienne Fishman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JavaScript and jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://adriennefishman.github.io/blog/2014/08/11/javascript-and-jquery/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-11T21:29:09-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adriennefishman.github.io/blog/2014/08/11/javascript-and-jquery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week at The Flatiron School, we began to learn about JavaScript and jQuery. Since JavaScript and jQuery are completely new to me, I thought it would be a good idea to research and discuss these topics.</p>

<p>JavaScript</p>

<p>Javascript is a scripting language. It does not stand by itself, but rather scripts another application, in this case, the browser. It is interpreted when it is run; it is not compiled.
JavaScript is platform-independent, meaning that it does not require any specific operating system or browser to work.
JavaScript was designed for use within a web browser. It is used for forms, slideshows and other interactive components.</p>

<p>jQuery</p>

<p>jQuery is a specific library of JavaScript code.
jQuery has been optimized to perform many common scripting functions and it does so using fewer lines of code.
jQuery has been optimized to work with a variety of browsers automatically, whereas JavaScript still has some issues with cross-browser compatibility.</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>The $ represents jQuery and it is how you access all of the functionality of the jQuery library.</p>

<p><a href="http://youmightnotneedjquery.com">http://youmightnotneedjquery.com</a>
This is a link to &ldquo;You Might Not Need jQuery.&rdquo; It is a useful resource that shows side-by-side examples of jQuery code and their &ldquo;vanilla Javascript counterparts.&rdquo; Even if you choose to use jQuery when you do not actually need it, the site urges you to &ldquo;at the very least, make sure you know what jQuery is doing for you, and what it&rsquo;s not.&rdquo; I found this to be very instructive as it gave me a deeper understanding of the syntax we have been using in our labs. The site shows jQuery and JavaScript code side-by-side for methods such as hide, show, append and before, which we have used this week.</p>

<p>Sources:
<a href="http://www.udemy.com/blog/jquery-vs-javascript/">http://www.udemy.com/blog/jquery-vs-javascript/</a>
<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/968461/why-javascript-is-called-as-scripting-language">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/968461/why-javascript-is-called-as-scripting-language</a>
<a href="http://youmightnotneedjquery.com">http://youmightnotneedjquery.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Post on Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://adriennefishman.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T11:05:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adriennefishman.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Hello World&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
